Guide to the East Side Tenants Council Records TAM.253
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
East Side Tenants Council Records
Bulk, 1955-1970
1937-1975
TAM.253
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.5 linear feet in one record carton and one manuscript box
The East Side Tenants Council was a community organization founded to advocate for tenants' rights on the Lower East Side of New York City in the mid-20th century. A local affiliate of the Metropolitan Council on Housing, its roots could be traced to 1930s tenant activism and 1950s-1960s neighborhood opposition to Robert Moses' reimagining of New York City. The council fought to hold or lower rent rates and improve the physical condition of buildings. This meant both building-level organization of tenants and navigating the bureaucratic paperwork of government agencies on behalf of individuals. The majority of the collection's documents were generated by the advocacy of tenants' representative Francesca Amato. Most these materials are filings, supporting work product, and correspondence with landlords and government housing agencies. As a part of her process, Amato took extensive notes on buildings' residents and the physical condition of their apartments, which document housing conditions in the Lower East Side during the 1950s-1970s. The collections also contains housing-related publications from government entities and other tenants' groups and one folder of photographs of buildings.
Amato, Francesca
East Side Tenants Council.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Archival Materials
Metropolitan Council on Housing Records (TAM 173)
The East Side Tenants Council was affiliated with the Met Council. Series III of TAM 173 contains several files of East Side Tenants Council records.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number 1950.185 is associated with this collection.
Historical/Biographical Note
The East Side Tenants Council was a community organization founded to advocate for tenants rights on the Lower East Side of New York City during the mid-20th century. It was a local affiliate of the Metropolitan Council on Housing.
The council's roots could be traced to the 1930s tenant activism of members of Communist Party and American Labor Party and neighborhood-based opposition to Robert Moses' reimagining of New York City. Tenants were organized at the building level for actions to stabilize or lower rent and to improve the physical condition of the often-dilapidated housing stock. Because the tenant-landlord relationship in New York City was strictly regulated, much of the advocacy took the form of navigating the paperwork of the city's bureaucracy on tenants' behalf. The council also provided assistance to individual tenants and ran housing clinics.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents the activities of the East Side Tenants Council and housing conditions in the Lower East Side of New York City in the 1950s-1970s. The majority of the documents were generated by the advocacy of tenants' representative Francesca Amato.
Actions represented in the collection are centered around a handful of buildings: 528 East 11th Street, 176-180 Avenue A, 122-128 Norfolk Street, and 252 East 7th Street. Most these materials are filings, supporting work product, and correspondence with landlords and government housing agencies. As a part of her process, Amato took extensive notes on buildings' residents and the physical condition of their apartments. These can be found in notebooks and in the files for actions, and they give insight into life on the Lower East Side. The East Side Tenants Council advocated for lower rents and improved building conditions, and the collection includes documents from actions pursued through the City of New York Department of Housing and Buildings, the State of New York Temporary State Housing Rent Commission, and the New York City Rent and Rehabilitation Administration, among others. The collections also contains housing-related publications from government entities and other tenants' groups and one folder of photographs of buildings.
Metropolitan Council on Housing (New York, N.Y.).; Community organization |z New York (State) |z New York.; Housing |z New York (State) |z New York.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.).; Rent control |z New York (State) |z New York.; Rent strikes |z New York (State) |z New York.; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z New York.; Women in community organization
- Alice P. Housing Photos, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Alley, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Apartment Inspections, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Building a Better New York: Final Report to Mayor Robert F. Wagner by Anthony Panuch, Mar 1, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Building Condition Notes, including 122 Norfolk Street; Notes regarding Health, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Buildings Department - Reports and Originals of Boiler and Western Union Night Letters, Block 00353, Lot 0057, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Buildings Department - Reports, Block 00353, Lot 0057, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- City Rent and Rehabilitation Administration - Rental Value Bulletins, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Clippings, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Collado Rental Data and Records, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Complaints to Department of Buildings, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Cooper Square Community Development Committee, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence - Duplicates [Original File Name], 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Council of Puerto Rican and and Spanish-American Organizations of Greater New York, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Crosses on Our Windows (Yorkville Save Our Homes Committee) and Clippings, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Manuel De Kony, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 528 East 11th Street, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
- 528 East 11th Street Hearing, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Guides and Papers on Housing Conditions and Tenants Rights, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Heat File, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Housing, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Individual, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Individual Tenant Assistance, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
- Inspection Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Letterhead and Forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Mixed Notices, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Multiple (City Rent and Rehabilitation Administration), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Notebooks, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 32-35)
- Notes and Complaint, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Jose Noya, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Ana Noyet, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Old Alley (Includes 176 Avenue A), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Emilio Ortiz, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- 176 Avenue A, Rear Building, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- 176,178, and 180 Avenue A, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- 122 Norfolk Street, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
- 122-128 Norfolk Street, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
- Antonina Previti, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Erminio Ramos, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Registration Requests, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Rent (Includes 176, 178, and 180 Avenue A), 1937-1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Rent (Includes 176, 178, and 180 Avenue A, and 503 East 11th Street), 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Rent Histories, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Tenant News (Metropolitan Council on Housing), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mak To, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 252 East 7th Street, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
- 252 East 7th Street and other Correspondence - AC385777, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 252 East 7th Street - Individual, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 252 East 7th Street - Individual Actions, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- 252 East 7th Street - Notebooks, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- 252 East 7th Street - Tenants' Multiple Application for Decrease in Rent, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Valle et al (169-171 Allen Street), 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)